Hi there my name’s John Green; this is Crash Course World History and today we’re going to talk about Jesus.
Xin chào, tôi là John Green, đây là Crash Course Lịch sử Thế giới, hôm nay chúng ta sẽ nói về Jesus.
So this is a Roman coin from around the time Jesus was born in the Roman Empire, and it
Đây là một đồng xu La Mã có từ thời chúa Jesus được sinh ra ở Đế chế Roma,
calls Augustus, the emperor, the son of God. So let’s just state at the outset that in
và chân dung đó là của Augustus, hoàng đế, là Con trời. Đi thẳng vào vấn đề:
4 BCE, being the son of God, or at least being the son of a god was not such an unusual thing.
Vào năm thứ 4 TCN, việc xưng là con trời, hay con của vị thần nào đó là điều khác thường.
But a poor Jew being the son of God — that was news.
Nhưng một người Do thái nghèo khổ tự xưng con trời là một sự kiện lớn.
[theme music]
[theme music]
Any understanding of Christianity has to start with Judaism, because Jesus was born a Jew,
Để hiểu được Thiên chúa giáo thì phải bắt đầu với Do thái giáo, vì Jesus là người Do thái,
and he grew up in the Jewish tradition. He was one of many teachers spreading his ideas
và lớn lên trong truyền thống Do thái. Ông là một trong những người truyền bá tư tưởng mới
in the Roman province of Judea at the time, and he was part of a messianic tradition that
đến vùng Judea của Đế chế Roma. Và ông là một phần của truyền thuyết về Chúa cứu thế
helps us understand why he was thought of not only teacher but something much, much more.
nên tại sao ông được coi không chỉ là một người thuyết pháp, mà là cái gì đó hơn thế.
Let’s go straight to the Thought Bubble today.
Cùng tiếp tục với Thought Bubble.
The people who would become the Jews, were just one of many tribal peoples eking out
Những người theo Do thái giáo khi đó là một trong những tộc người sống ở
an existence in that not-very fertile crescent world of Mesopotamia after the agricultural revolution.
vùng Trăng lưỡi liềm Màu mỡ Lưỡng Hà sau cách mạng nông nghiệp.
The Hebrews initially worshiped many gods, making sacrifices to them in order to bring
Người Hebrew vốn thờ đa thần, hiến tế cho họ để mong được
good weather and good fortune. But they eventually developed a religion centered around an idea
thời tiết thuận hòa và cuộc sống no đủ. Nhưng họ đã phát triển một thứ tôn giáo với tư tưởng
that would become key to the other great western religions.
sau này trở thành tư tưởng chính của các tôn giáo lớn phương Tây.
This was monotheism, the idea that there is only one true god (or at least that if there
Đó là thuyết đơn thần, ý tưởng rằng chỉ có duy nhất một thần (hay nếu có
are other gods around, they are total lameoids). The Hebrews developed a second concept that
các thần khác, thì chỉ là râu ria, làm nền). Người Hebrew có một quan niệm nữa,
is key to their religion as well: the idea of the covenant, a deal with God.
tư tưởng chính trong tôn giáo của họ: ý tưởng về Thỏa ước, một thỏa thuận với Thượng đế.
The main man in this, the big macher was Abraham. Not to make this too much of a scripture lesson,
Người đóng vai trò chủ chốt trong việc này, là Abraham. Tôi không muốn giảng đạo ở đây,
but it’s kind of hard to understand the Jews without understanding Abraham, or Abram
Nhưng khó mà hiểu được người Do thái nếu không biết về Abraham, kể cả trước khi
as he was known before he had his big conversation with God. Recorded in Genesis 17: "When Abram
ông có cuộc giao tiếp với Thượng đế. Trong cuốn Chúa sáng thế 17 có ghi: "Lúc Abraham 99 tuổi,
was ninety years and nine, the LORD appeared to Abram, and said unto him, 'I am the Almighty
vị thánh xuất hiện và nói với ông, 'Ta là Chúa Toàn năng,
God; walk before me, and be thou perfect.' " And I’m a make a covenant with you and
theo ta, và ngươi sẽ trở nên toàn hảo.' Ta và người thỏa ước,
a bunch of cool things will happen like you’re gonna have kids and your descendants will
và nhiều điều tuyệt vời sẽ đến, như ngươi sẽ có con đàn cháu đống
number the stars and you can have all the land of Canaan forever, it’s gonna be awesome.
và vùng Cận Đông mãi mãi, điều đó sẽ rất tuyệt.
I’m paraphrasing by the way, Thought Bubble.
Tôi đang diễn giải một tí, Thought Bubble.
So God promised that Abram would have kids with his wife even though the dude was already
Thượng đế hứa là Abraham sẽ có con với vợ mình cho dù cụ đã 99 tuổi,
like 99, but there was a catch: "This is my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me
nhưng có một cái bẫy : " Đây là thỏa ước của ta, chúng ta phải tuân thủ nó, giữa ta và ngươi
and you and thy seed after thee; every man child among you shall be circumcised." Keep
và cả các đời sau; những đứa con trai của ngươi sẽ được cắt bao quy đầu."
it PG-13, Thought Bubble.
Nhớ cảnh báo PG-13 nhé, Thought Bubble.
Now that is asking a lot from a guy, especially a 99-year-old geezer like Abram living in
Đó là một thách thức lớn đối với một người, nhất là một ông cụ 99 tuổi như Abraham
a time before general anesthesia. But those were the terms of the deal, and in exchange
khi mà chưa có gây mê, gây tê gì cả. Nhưng đây là thỏa ước, và đổi lại,
God had chosen Abraham and his descendants to be a great nation. From this we get the
Thượng đế đã cho Abraham và hậu duệ là một dân tộc vĩ đại. Từ đó suy ra,
expression that the Jews are the Chosen people.
người Do thái được Thượng đế lựa chọn.
Thanks for keeping it clean, Thought Bubble.
Cảm ơn vì đã không rườm rà, Thought Bubble.
So, some important things about this god:
Một số điều quan trọng về Thượng đế:
One, singularity. He — and I’m using the masculine pronoun because that’s what Hebrew
Một, Ông là duy nhất. Tôi dùng đại từ đó vì người Hebrew cũng gọi như thế.
prayers use — does not want you to put any gods before Him.
Ông không muốn ở sau ai cả.
He is also transcendent, having always existed and he is deeply personal – he chats with
Người cũng rất siêu phàm, luôn hiện hữu và rất con người. Ông nói chuyện với
prophets, sends locusts, etc. But he doesn’t take corporeal form like the Greek and Roman Gods do.
các nhà tiên tri, mang châu chấu đến, vv. Nhưng ông không có hình hài như các vị thần Hy lạp và Roma.
He is also involved in history, like he will destroy cities, and bring floods, and determine
Ông cũng góp phần làm nên lịch sử, như tàn phá thành phố, gây lũ, và định đoạt các cuộc chiến,
the outcome of wars, and possibly football games. Stan, no! FOOTBALL games!
và có thể cả kết quả trận bóng. Stan, không phải. Là Bóng đá cơ.
Probably most important to us today, and certainly most important to Jesus, this god demands
Có lẽ điều quan trọng nhất, với chúng ta và tất nhiên là với Jesus, thượng đế muốn
moral righteousness and social justice. So, this is the god of the Hebrews, Yahweh, and
sự liêm chính và công lý. Nên, đây là vị thượng đế của ngưới Hebrew, còn gọi là Yahweh,
despite many ups and downs, the Jewish people have stuck with him for- according to the
và dù có nhiều biến cố, người Do thái vẫn gắn bó với ông
Hebrew calendar, at least- over 5700 years.
trong hơn 5,700 năm - tính theo lịch Hebrew.
And He has stuck by them too, despite the Jews being, on occasion, something of a disappointment
Và ông chung thủy với họ, dù người Do thái đôi lúc cũng làm ông thất vọng.
to him. Which leads to various miseries, and also to a tradition of prophets who speak
Điều này mang đến những bất hạnh, và thường cũng có những nhà tiên tri,
for God and warn the people to get back on the right path lest there be more miseries.
thay lời thượng đế cảnh báo con người trở về với chính đạo để tránh điều bất hạnh.
Which brings us back to our friends, the Romans. By the time that Jesus was born, the land
Điều này gợi nhớ đến người Roma. Đến khi Jesus giáng sinh, vùng đất
of the Israelites had been absorbed into the Roman Empire as the province of Judea. At
của người Do thái đã bị sáp nhập vào Đế chế Roma làm tỉnh Judea.
the time of Jesus’s birth, Judea was under the control of Herod the Great, best known
Khi đó, Judea dưới sự kiểm soát của Herod Đại vương, người nổi tiếng với việc
for building the massive temple in Jerusalem, that the Romans would later destroy.
xây ngôi đền lớn ở Jerusalem mà sau này người Roman phá hủy.
And by the time Jesus died, an expanded Judea was under the rule of Herod Antipater. Also,
Và lúc Jesus chết, vùng Judea mở rộng là dưới sự cai trị của Herod Antipater.
unhelpfully, known as Herod. Both Herods ultimately took their orders from the Romans, and they
Cả hai đều thường được gọi là Herod, đều theo lệnh của Roma.
both show up on the list of rulers who are oppressive to the Jews, partly because there’s
Cả hai đều nằm trong danh sách những người áp bức người Do thái, một phần vì
never that much religious freedom in an empire.
làm gì có nhiều tự do tôn giáo trong một đế chế.
Unless you are, wait for it... The Mongols [Mongoltage]
Trừ khi bạn là, chờ chút....Người Mông cổ.
or the Persians. Also, they were Hellenizers, bringing in Greek theater and architecture,
hoặc người Ba Tư. Ở đó cũng có người Hy lạp, với vốn kịch nghệ, kiến trúc và sự duy lý.
and rationalism. And in response to those Hellenistic influences, there were a lot of
Để chống lại những ảnh hưởng của văn hóa Hy lạp, cũng có nhiều nhà thuyết giáo
preachers trying to get the Jews to return to the traditions and the godly ways of the
cố gắng đưa người Do thái trở lại với những truyền thống tôn giáo trong quá khứ,
past, including the Sadducees, and the Pharisees, and the Essenes, and the Zealots.
bao gồm Sadducees, Pharisees, Essenes, và Zealots.
And one of those preachers, who didn’t fit comfortably into any of these four groups,
Và một trong những nhà thuyết giáo, người không nằm trong nhóm nào kể trên,
was Jesus of Nazareth. Jesus was a preacher who spread his message of peace, love and,
là Jesus ở Nazareth. Jesus là nhà thuyết giáo với thông điệp hòa bình, tình yêu và,
above all, justice, across Judea over the course of his actually average-length life for his time.
trên hết là công lý, trên khắp Judea trong cả cuộc đời.
He was remarkably charismatic, attracting a small but incredibly loyal group of followers,
Ông có sức lôi cuốn tuyệt diệu, thu hút được một nhóm tông đồ nhỏ nhưng cực kỳ trung thành.
and he was said to perform miracles — although it’s worth noting that miracles weren’t
Và ông cũng được cho là có phép màu - dù cần lưu ý là phép màu không phải là cái gì
terribly uncommon at the time.
quá bất thường vào thời đó.
Jesus’s message was particularly resonant to the poor and downtrodden and pretty radical
Thông điệp của Jesus đặc biệt được hưởng ứng bởi người nghèo và người bị áp bức và khá quyết liệt
in its anti-authoritarian stance. He said it was easier for a camel to get through the
với lập trường chống độc đoán. Ông nói, một con lạc đà chui qua lỗ kim là việc
eye of a needle than for a rich man to get to heaven, he said the meek were blessed,
dễ hơn là một người giàu được lên thiên đàng. Ông nói ở hiền gặp lành.
that the last would be first and the first would be last — all of which was kind of
Tất cả những giáo lý đó là mối đe dọa
threatening to the powers that be, who accordingly had him arrested, tried and then executed
đối với giới cầm quyền, những kẻ nhất trí bắt ông, xét xử và hành hình
in the normal method of killing rebels at that time: crucifixion.
theo cách thường làm với kẻ phiến loạn: đóng đinh chữ thập.
Also, just to put this question to bed, the Romans crucified Jesus, because he was a
Hãy nghĩ về điều này: Người Roma hành hình Jesus, vì ông là sự đe dọa
threat to their authority. Later traditions saying that the Jews killed Jesus? Very unfortunate, also, very untrue.
quyền lực của họ. Truyền thuyết sau này lại nói người Do thái giết Jesus, điều rất không đúng.
We’re not going to discuss Jesus’s divinity, because:
Chúng ta sẽ không bàn về sự thần thánh của Giêsu, vì:
1. This isn’t a theology class, and 2. Flame wars on the Internet make me so uncomfortable that
1. Đây không phải là lớp thần học và 2. Ngọn lửa chiến tranh trên mạng khiến tôi khó chịu
I have to turn to camera 2. Hi there camera 2, I’m here to remind you that
nên phải chuyển qua camera 2. Chào Camera 2, tôi nhắc rằng
3. Fighting over such things, like fighting over whether the proverbial cake is a lie,
3. Chiến đấu vì những chuyện tào lao, như việc cái bánh này có phải là thật không,
rarely accomplishes anything, plus 4. What matters to us is the historical fact
sẽ khó mà đi đến đâu, thêm nữa, 4. Điều ta bận tâm là sự thật lịch sử
that people at the time believed that Jesus was the Messiah, the Anointed One, the son
rằng thời ấy người ta tin Jesus là Đấng Cứu thế, là con của Thượng đế.
of God. And they believed that he would return some day to redeem the world.
Và người ta tin rằng ông sẽ trở lại để giải thoát thế giới.
Which leads us to two questions about Christianity:
Điều đó dẫn đến hai câu hỏi về Thiên chúa giáo:
First, Why did this small group of people believe this? And second, why and how did
Thứ nhất, tại sao nhóm người này lại tin vào điều này? Và thứ 2, tại sao và làm thế nào
that belief become so widespread?
niềm tin đó lại được lan rộng như thế?
So why would people believe that Jesus was the Messiah?
Vậy tại sao người ta tin rằng Jesus là Chúa cứu thế?
First. The Jews had a long tradition of believing that a savior who would come to them in a
Thứ nhất. Người Do thái vốn từ lâu tin rằng một vị cứu tinh sẽ đến với họ
time of trouble. And Judea under the rule of Herod and the Romans... definitely a time of trouble.
trong lúc khó khăn. Judea dưới sự cai trị của Herod và người Roma...chắc chắn là thời điểm đó.
And many of the prophecies about this savior point to someone whose life looks a lot like
Và nhiều lời tiên tri về vị cứu thế này nói đến người có nhiều nét giống Jesus.
Jesus's. For instance, Isaiah 53 says the person will be misunderstood and mistreated,
Ví dụ, Sách Isaiah-chương 53 nói rằng người đó sẽ bị hiểu nhầm và bị ngược đãi,
just like Jesus was: “He was despised, and rejected by men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted
giống như Jesus: "Người bị khinh miệt và xua đuổi, chịu sự buồn đau, và ta
with grief: and as one from whom men hide their face he was despised; and we didn't respect him.”
nên xấu hổ vì đã coi thường và không coi trọng người."
And a lot of the prophecies like Daniel 7:14, for instance, explained that when the Messiah
Và nhiều lời sấm truyền, như của Daniel, nói rằng khi Đấng Cứu thế xuất hiện
comes there will be this awesome, new, everlasting kingdom. And that had to sound pretty good
thì sẽ có một  vương quốc mới vĩ đại và trường tồn. Điều đó khá hấp dẫn
to people who’d had their autonomy taken away from them.
với những người bị tước mất chủ quyền.
So some religious Jews saw Jesus in those prophecies and came to believe either during
Nên, một số người Do thái sùng đạo trong một thời gian dài xem Jesus
his life or shortly thereafter, that he was the messiah. Most of them thought the new
như người ứng nghiệm sấm truyền, là đấng cứu thế. Họ nghĩ rằng
everlasting kingdom was right around the corner, which is probably why no one bothered to write
vương quốc trường tồn sắp thành hiện thực, nên người ta đã nói nhiều
down much about the life of Jesus for several decades, by which time it was clear that we
về cuộc đời Jesus trong vài thập kỷ, cho đến khi nhận ra rằng
might have to wait a bit for this brilliant new everlasting kingdom.
có thể phải chờ đợi tiếp một vương quốc vĩ đại trường tồn.
I should note, by the way, that the idea of a messiah was not unique to the Jews at the
Tôi nhấn mạnh rằng ý tưởng về Chúa cứu thế thời bấy giờ không phải là của riêng người Do thái.
time. Even the Romans got in on the action, for instance, the Roman poet Virgil wrote
Người Roma thậm chí còn đi xa hơn, như nhà thờ Virgil viết về một câu bé:
of a boy who: “Shall free the earth from never-ceasing fear, he shall receive the life
"Hãy giải thoát cho thế giới khỏi nỗi sợ hãi vô bờ, hãy sống
of gods, and see Heroes with gods commingling.” Sound familiar?
một cuộc đời thần thánh, cùng với khí chất anh hùng." Nghe quen không?
But Virgil was writing about Emperor Augustus in that poem, not Jesus, which points again
Nhưng Virgil viết về Hoàng đế Augustus, không phải Giêsu, nên một lần nữa cho thấy
to the similarities between the two. Both called sons of God. Both sent to free the
sự giống nhau của hai người. Cả hai đều được gọi là Con của Thượng đế. Cả hai đều được giáng trần
earth from never-ceasing fear. But one ruled the largest empire in the world; and the other
để giải cứu thế giới khỏi khổ đau. Chỉ là một người cai trị đế chế rộng lớn nhất, và một người
believed that empire, and the world, needed to change dramatically.
cho rằng đế chế đó, và thế giới cần có sự thay đổi lớn.
So why did the less wealthy and famous son of God become by far the more influential?
Nhưng tại sao người con ít giàu có và ít nổi tiếng hơn lại có sức ảnh hưởng lớn hơn?
Well, here are three possible historical reasons:
Có 3 lý do:
Reason #1: The Romans continued to make things bad for the Jews. In fact, things got much
Lý do #1: Người Roma tiếp tục ngược đãi người Do thái. Đặc biệt
worse for the Jews, especially after they launched a revolt between 66-73 CE, which did not go well.
tồi tệ hơn sau khi họ đàn áp cuộc nổi dậy từ năm 66 đến 73.
By the time the dust settled, the Romans had destroyed the Temple and expelled the Jews
Đến khi sự việc lắng xuống, người Roma đã phá ngôi đền Do thái và đuổi họ
from Judea, beginning what we now know as the Jewish Diaspora.
khỏi Judea, khởi đầu tình trạng phân tán của Cộng đồng Do thái.
And without a Temple or geographic unity, the Jews had to solidify what it meant to
Không có nơi thờ tự và địa bàn chung, người Do thái phải củng cố lại những yếu tố cốt lõi
be a Jew and what the basic tenants of the religion were. This forced the followers of
và dịa bàn chính cho tôn giáo đứng chân. Điều này buộc các tông đồ của Jesus
Jesus to make a decision: were they going to continue to be Jews following stricter
phải lựa chọn: tiếp tục theo Do thái giáo với những luật lệ hà khắc,
laws set forth by rabbis, or were they going to be something else.
hay trở thành cái gì đó khác.
The decision to open up their religion to non-Jews, people who weren’t part of the
Quyết định về việc mở rộng kết nạp những người không phải dân Do thái, không ràng buộc bởi Thỏa ước,
covenant, is the central reason that Christianity could become a world religion instead of just
là lý do chính khiến Thiên chúa giáo có thể trở thành tôn giáo toàn cầu, thay vì
a sect of Judaism. And it probably didn’t hurt that the main proponent of sticking with
chỉ là một nhánh của Do thái giáo. Và có lẽ sẽ không có gì xảy ra nếu người chủ trương ở lại
Judaism was James, Jesus’s brother, who was killed by the Romans.
với Do thái giáo không phải là James, người anh em của Jesus, người bị sát hại bởi Roma.
Reason #2: Is related to Reason #1 and it’s all about a dude named Saul. No, not that
Lý do #2: Liên quan đến lí do thứ nhất và liên quan đến một vị tên Saul. Không phải Saul đó.
Saul. Yes, Saul of Tarsus, thank you.
Đúng rồi, Saul quê ở Tarsus cơ, cảm ơn.
Saul, having received a vision on the road to Damascus, became Paul and began visiting
Saul có tầm nhìn về con đường đến Damascus, đổi tên gọi thành Paul và bắt đầu thăm viếng
and sending letters to Jesus followers throughout the Mediterranean. And it was Paul who emphatically
và gửi thư cho các tông đồ của Jesus khắp vùng Địa Trung Hải. Đó chính là Paul đã tuyên bố rõ ràng
declared that Jesus followers did NOT have to be Jews, that they did not have to be circumcised
rằng tông đồ của Jesus không cần phải là người Do thái, không phải cắt bao quy đầu
or keep to Jewish laws or any of that stuff.
hay tuân thủ theo luật Do thái, hay bất cứ điều gì liên quan.
This opened the floodgates for thousands of people to convert to this new religion. And
Việc này đã mở rộng cửa cho hàng nghìn người cải đạo sang tôn giáo mới này. Và
the other thing to remember about Paul is that he was a Roman citizen, which meant that
điều khác nữa để nhớ về Paul là ông là công dân Roma, nghĩa là
he could travel freely throughout the Roman Empire. This allowed him to make his case
ông có thể tự do đi lại trong Đế chế. Nó cho phép ông có thể dễ dàng
to lots of different people and facilitated the geographic spread of Christianity.
kết nạp được nhiều người và mở rộng vùng ảnh hưởng của Thiên chúa giáo.
Oh, it’s time for the open letter? Alright. An open letter, to the fish.
Đến giờ đọc thư ngỏ rồi à? Được. Một bức thư ngỏ gửi loài cá.
But first, lets see what’s in the secret compartment today. Oh, Stan. It’s my favorite
Nhưng trước hết, hãy xem có gì trong ngăn tủ bí mật hôm nay. Oh, Stan. Đó là
album Jesus Christ Superstar, finally available in my favorite format, the cassette. Did I
album yêu thích của tôi Jesus Christ Superstar, lại còn dưới định dạng mà tôi thích, băng đài.
color-coordinate my shirt to Jesus Christ Superstar? Yes.
Tôi mặc màu áo giống màu cuôn băng này được không?
Dear Ichthys, So check this out: In the first century when it was still super underground
Ichthy thân mến, Vào thế kỷ đầu tiên, khi Thiên chúa giáo còn trong trứng nước
and hipster to be a Christian, you were a secret symbol of Christianity, used to kind
với những tín đồ cấp tiến đầu tiên, cậu là biểu tượng bí mật của Thiên chúa giáo,
of hide from the Romans. Ichthys, the Greek word for fish, was an acronym and it was a
để che mắt Roma. Ichthy là một từ viết tắt tiếng Hy lạp để chỉ loài cá.
super clever way to talk about religion without anyone knowing that you were talking about it.
Đó là cách không ngoan để nói đến tôn giáo mà không ai ngờ đến.
But you’ll never guess what happened - even in places where it’s completely fine to
Nhưng cậu không thể tưởng tượng nổi điều đã diễn ra - thậm chí ở những nơi
talk about Christianity now and to use, you know, regular Christian symbols, like the
mà Thiên chúa giáo và các biểu tượng của nó được thoải mái bàn luận và sử dụng,
cross, you have had a huge resurgence thanks to the plastic automobile decal industry.
như chữ thập chẳng hạn, cậu có sự hồi sinh đáng kinh ngạc nhờ công nghệ trang trí ô tô.
I mean seriously, Ichthys, I haven’t seen a comeback like this since Jesus.
Thật đấy, biểu tượng cá ạ, tôi chưa từng thấy sự trở lại nào ấn tượng như thế kể từ đầu Công nguyên.
Best wishes, John Green
Thân mến, John Green
And lastly, Christianity was born and flourished an empire with a common language that allowed
Và cuối cùng, Kitô giáo được khai sinh và hưng khởi một đế chế với ngôn ngữ chung
for its spread. And crucially, it was also an Empire in decline.
giúp nó lan tỏa. Và quan trọng là đúng vào lúc một đế chế suy tàn.
Like even by the end of the first century CE, Rome was on its way down. And for the
Thậm chí đến cuối thế kỉ thứ nhất, Roma vẫn đang trong quá trình sụp đổ.
average person, and even for some elites, things weren’t as good as they had been,
Với giới trung lưu và thậm chí một số thuộc giới thượng lưu, mọi chuyện không còn tốt đẹp như xưa.
if fact they were getting worse so fast that you might have thought the end of the world was coming.
Thực tế, chúng tệ đi nhanh đến mức mà người ta nghĩ rằng ngày tận thế sắp đến nơi.
And Roman religion offered no promise of an afterlife, and a bunch of squabbling whiny
Và trong tôn giáo Roma thì không có kiếp sau, mà lại nhiều thần thánh suốt ngày cãi lộn -
gods - sorry if I offended adherents to Roman religion, but seriously, they squabble. So
xin lỗi nếu làm mất lòng các tín đồ theo tôn giáo Roma. Nhưng họ hay cãi nhau thật.
even though early Christians were persecuted by the Roman Empire and sometimes fed to the
Nên dù các tín đồ Thiên chúa có bị Roma ngược đãi và đôi khi làm mồi
lions and other animals, the religion continued to grow, albeit slowly.
cho sư tử và loài thú khác, thì tôn giáo này vẫn tiếp tục phát triển, dù hơi chậm.
But then as the Roman decline continued, Emperor Constantine allowed the worship of Jesus and
Nhưng khi khi Roma tiếp tục suy tàn, Hoàng đế Constantine đã cho phép thờ phượng Jesus
then eventually converted to Christianity himself. And then the religion really took
và cuối cùng, chính ông cải đạo sang Thiên chúa. Và sau đó thì tôn giáo này bắt đầu phát triển mạnh.
off. I mean, Rome wasn’t what it used to be, but everybody still wanted to be like
Roma đã sớm không còn in hình hoàng đế lên tiền xu như thường lệ.
the Emperor. And soon enough there was a new son of God on coins.
mà chuyển sang hình ảnh một người Con của Thượng đế mới toanh.
Thanks for watching. See you next week.
Cảm ơn đã theo dõi. Hẹn gặp lại tuần sau.
Crash Course is produced and directed by Stan Muller, our script supervisor is Danica Johnson.
Crash Course is produced and directed by Stan Muller, our script supervisor is Danica Johnson.
The show is written by my high school history teacher Raoul Meyer and myself and our graphics
The show is written by my high school history teacher Raoul Meyer and myself and our graphics
team is Thought Bubble.
team is Thought Bubble.
As only 62 million of you guessed last week, the Phrase of the Week was "Chipotle Burrito";
As only 62 million of you guessed last week, the Phrase of the Week was "Chipotle Burrito";
if you want to guess at this week’s Phrase of the Week or suggest future ones, you can
if you want to guess at this week’s Phrase of the Week or suggest future ones, you can
do so in Comments where you can also ask questions about today’s video that will be answered,
do so in Comments where you can also ask questions about today’s video that will be answered,
hopefully, by our team of historians.
hopefully, by our team of historians.
Thanks for watching Crash Course, and as we say in my hometown, Don't Forget To Be Awesome.
Thanks for watching Crash Course, and as we say in my hometown, Don't Forget To Be Awesome.
Ow... again.
Ow... again.